"Restoring Our Natural GLP-1
Satiety Circuit with Fiber"
L-cells, the specialized cells
lining our digestive tract
that produce
appetite-suppressing hormones
like GLP-1, have receptors
on their surface
that respond to carbohydrates,
proteins, and fats,
as well as detect
bitter compounds
like quinine in tonic water
that I’ve talked about before,
as well as pungent molecules,
as I detailed
in my video on spices.
But if these cells churn out
appetite-suppressing hormones
in response to detecting carbs,
proteins, and fats,
why do we have
an obesity epidemic?
Why are so many people
gaining so much weight?
The problem is the majority
of GLP-1-producing L cells
are located at the lower part
of our digestive tract,
way at the end
of our small intestine,
known as the distal ileum,
and especially in our colon.
Unfortunately, the majority
of digested nutrients
are absorbed
in the upper GI tract
high in our small intestines,
so don’t reach
the distal ileum and colon
where L-cells
are highly abundant,
and so, we may rarely activate
a natural satiety mechanism
known as the ileal brake,
which you may remember
from my Evidence-Based
Weight Loss presentation.
The ileal brake is the
intestinal feedback mechanism
that tamps down our hunger.
As soon as calories
reach the ilium,
the end of our small intestine,
L-cells are activated,
and GLP-1 is produced,
which puts the brakes
on eating more.
Our appetite is dialed down,
and the rate at which food
leaves our stomach slows.
This can be shown
experimentally.
If you insert a 9-foot tube
down people’s throats
and drip in any calories,
fat, protein, or sugar,
you can activate
the ileal brake.
Then, when they sit down
to an all-you-can-eat meal,
(compared to individuals
in the placebo group
who had just gotten a squirt
of water through the tube),
they eat
over 100 calories less.
With the ileal brake on,
you just don’t feel as hungry.
You feel just as full,
eating significantly less.
That’s the ileal brake
in action.
But our natural GLP-1
satiety mechanism fails,
because most food components
are rapidly digested
and absorbed at the beginning
of our small intestine
and don’t make it down to
the end of the small intestine
where our GLP-1 secreting cells
are concentrated.
Well, that’s dumb.
Why would our body design
an appetite regulation system
based on calories
ending up in our colon,
when most calories
get absorbed way before that
no matter how much we eat?
Because when we were evolving,
there was no such thing
as table sugar.
There was no such thing
as Wonder Bread.
No such thing as vegetable oil.
For the millions of years before
we began to sharpen spears,
mill grains, or boil sugarcane,
our entire physiology
is presumed to have evolved
in the context of eating
what our great ape cousins did,
a diet comprised of leaves,
roots, fruits, and nuts.
W e started using tools
during the Paleolithic period,
which only goes back
about two million years,
but we and other great apes
have been evolving
since the Miocene era,
which goes back as far
as 20 million years.
So, for as much
as the first 90 percent
of our hominoid existence,
our body evolved
on mostly whole plant foods.
Here’s why that matters.
Animal cells are encased only
in easily digestible membranes,
which allow the enzymes
in our gut to effortlessly
liberate the calories
within a steak, for example.
Plant cells,
on the other hand,
have cell walls
that are made out of fiber,
which acts as an indigestible
physical barrier;
so, many of those calories
remain trapped
until the good gut bugs
in our colon eat that fiber
and spill out the contents
of plant cells
to signal GLP-1 release.
When we get our calories,
our protein, fat, and carbs
(like the sugars in milk)
from animal foods,
they get absorbed early
in the small intestine
and never get to activate
many of the satiety cells
that secrete GLP-1 hormones,
which are
concentrated farther down.
It’s the same when you consume
processed plant foods.
Chug down sugar water,
white flour, and oil,
and the exact same thing
happens.
But what if you walled off
your calories,
in other words,
tried to make sure
as many of your calories
as possible,
your protein, your carbs,
your fat,
were encased in cell walls?
In other words,
from whole, intact, plant foods?
Let’s say you eat a nut.
No matter how well you chew,
tiny bits of nut
containing hundreds
of thousands of intact cells
are going to make it
down to your colon,
where the fat can be released
by fiber-eating bacteria
to activate GLP-1 secretion.
You can see the bacteria
breaking into the cells
and nom-nomming
all the goodies.
The same happens when you eat
an apple or steel-cut oats.
Instead of all the sugar
and starch
getting absorbed earlier,
like if you drank apple juice
or ate a cracker,
some of the carbs
spill out further down
to activate
your satiety hormones.
Even though the milling
of whole grains into flour
can break open
all the grains’ cell walls,
whole-grain bread is still
better than white bread,
because whole-grain
at least has extra fiber
that makes it
down to our colon.
There, our good gut bugs
can turn the fiber
into short-chain fatty acids
that can activate GLP-1
secretion on their own.
And, fiber has
a gelling property
that can trap
other calories in the meal
and pull them farther down
the intestine.
Chug a third-of-a-cup
(80 ml) of oil
on a high-fiber diet,
and more than twice as much fat
makes it to your colon
than when you have
the same amount of oil
on a low-fiber diet.
In other words,
even if you ate a donut
on an otherwise
high-fiber diet,
some of the donut calories
could still make it far enough
down to help dial down
your hunger.
So, we have to make sure
our calories
get all the way down to the end
of our small intestine
for a sustained
release of GLP-1.
And dietary fiber
can help do that
by slowing the digestion
and absorption of the calories
we eat to maximize
their activity
in sustaining the secretion
of GLP-1.
So, part of
the "slow digestion strategy"
to sustain GLP-1 secretion
is dietary fiber to slow down
the digestion of nutrients.
This strategy has been proposed
as a dietary approach
to mimic the function
of bariatric surgery.
Because certain procedures
can entail
literally cutting out
part of your small intestine,
nutrients get dumped
further down,
causing a big GLP-1
ileal brake response.
So, the modern medical solution
to this mismatch
between the foods
we were built to eat,
that naturally activate
satiety circuits,
and the processed junk
we’re now being sold,
is to physically,
surgically change our anatomy
to force it to the end
of our gut,
or inject GLP-1 mimicking drugs,
so we get GLP-1 activation
regardless of what we eat.
It’s funny, you’ll read
how "almost no nutrients"
make it down to where
the GLP-1 producing cells are,
"under normal conditions."
But by "normal"
they mean donuts for breakfast.
When, really,
normal-for-our-species
is eating
so many unprocessed plant foods
that we’re knocking down
triple-digit grams
of fiber every day.
That entails massive amounts
of whole plant foods.
So, to restore
our natural satiety circuits,
we can go under the knife,
under the needle,
or just eat
the way nature intended.